Register of the Robert Douglas Stuart Papers, 1944-1975
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Douglas Stuart Papers
1944-1975
84025
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope (9 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, printed matter, and memorabilia, relating to American politics, American relations with Canada, and activities of the Canadian-American Committee.
Stuart, R. Douglas (Robert Douglas), 1886-1975
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1886, January 20 Born, Glencoe, Illinois
1906 Graduated from Princeton University
Started with Quaker Oats Company
1948-1953 Treasurer, Republican National Committee
1953-1956 Ambassador to Canada
1956-1962 Chairman, Quaker Oats Company
1957 Co-founder and co-chairman, Canadian-American Committee
1975, January 5 Died, Lake Forest, Illinois
Canadian-American Committee.; Canada--Foreign relations--United States.; Canada.; Diplomats--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Canada.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1959-1975 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Invitation cards and memorial resolutions, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Invitations, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resolutions adopted by various organizations in memory of Robert D. Stuart, 1975 (Folder 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1952-1974 (Box 1)
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Adams, Sherman, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Antep, Aleph von, 1956 (Folder 4)
  - Benson, Ezra T., 1957-1959 (Folder 5)
  - Campney, Ralph O., 1956-1957 (Folder 6)
  - Carpentier, Charles F., 1960 (Folder 7)
  - Casey, R. G., 1957 (Folder 8)
  - Cassels, Gordon, 1956 (Folder 9)
  - Church, Marguerite Stitt, 1961-1962 (Folder 10)
  - Coupland, James P., 1956 (Folder 11)
  - Dixon, Wesley M., 1959 (Folder 12)
  - Drew, George, 1956-1957 (Folder 13)
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1956-1959 (Folder 14)
  - Dunn, Lady, 1957 (Folder 15)
  - Edwards, Mrs. C. M., 1959 (Folder 16)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1957-1960 (Folder 17)
  - Ford, Gerald R., 1974 (Folder 18)
  - Gardiner, James G., 1956 (Folder 19)
  - Garin, Vasco Vieira, 1956 (Folder 20)
  - Graham, Howard D., 1956 (Folder 21)
  - Graham, John, 1956 (Folder 22)
  - Harris, Albert W., 1957 (Folder 23)
  - Hauge, Gabriel, 1958 (Folder 24)
  - Herter, Christian A., 1958-1959 (Folder 25)
  - Hoover, Herbert C., 1957-1961 (Folder 26)
  - Howe, C. D., 1956-1961 (Folder 27)
  - Humphrey, George M., 1957 (Folder 28)
  - Kalamazoo Company, Michigan, 1956 (Folder 29)
  - Leger, Jules, 1958 (Folder 30)
  - Lesage, Jean, 1960 (Folder 31)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1960 (Folder 32)
  - MacMillan, H. R., 1956 (Folder 33)
  - McDonald, E. C., 1956 (Folder 34)
  - McDougald, J. Bethume, 1956 (Folder 35)
  - Merchant, Livingston T., 1956-1957 (Folder 36)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1958-1960, 1973 (Folder 37)
  - Rand, I. C., 1956 (Folder 38)
  - Schmon, Arthur A., 1957 (Folder 39)
  - Shultz, Vester M., 1956-1958 (Folder 40)
  - Stratton, William G., 1959-1960 (Folder 41)
  - United States. Embassy (Canada), 1956-1957 (Folder 42)
  - Weeks, Sinclair, 1952 (Folder 43)
  - Whitney, John H., 1957 (Folder 44)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1944-1965 (Box 2)
  Autographs, by-laws, correspondence, lists, minutes, reports, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Autographs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 1)
    - U.S. Representatives (Folder 2)
    - U.S. Senators (Folder 3)
  - Dulles, John Foster. Tribute by Richard M. Nixon, Printed copy, 1959. (Folder 4)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1953 (Folder 5)
  - Foundation for American Agriculture, 1944-1955 (Folder 6)
  - Herbert Hoover Birthplace Foundation, Inc., 1958-1965 (Folder 7)
- AMBASSADOR TO CANADA, 1953-1956 (Box 3-9)
  Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings relating to Ambassador Stuart's appointed term in Canada (Box 3)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 1)
    - 1955 (Folder 2)
    - 1956 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1956
    - General
      - A-E (Folder 4-8)
      - F-M (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
      - N-Z (Box 5, Folder 1-11)
    - Adams, Sherman (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Benson, Ezra T. (Folder 2)
    - Brownell, Herbert, Jr. (Folder 3)
    - Business Advisory Council, U.S. Department of Commerce (Folder 4)
    - Claxton, Brooke (Folder 5)
    - Dempsey, John B., II (Folder 6)
    - Diplomatic corps, Ottawa (Folder 7)
    - Douglas, James H., Jr. (Folder 8)
    - Heeney, A. D. P. (Folder 9)
    - Heffelfinger, F. Peavey (Folder 10)
    - Herbert Hoover Birthplace Foundation, Inc. (Folder 11)
    - Hobby, Oveta Culp (Folder 12)
    - Hoover, Herbert, Jr. (Folder 13)
    - Horsey, Outerbridge (Folder 14)
    - Howe, C. D. (Folder 15)
    - Humphrey, George M. (Folder 16)
    - Junior Achievement, Washington, D.C. (Folder 17)
    - Randall, Clarence B. (Folder 18)
    - Republican National Committee (Folder 19)
    - Robbins, Laurence B. (Folder 20)
    - Saint Lawrence Seaway Development Corporation (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Stevens, Robert T. (Folder 2)
    - Stevenson, John (Folder 3)
    - Talbott, Harold E. (Folder 4)
    - Thomas, Charles S. (Folder 5)
    - Weeks, Sinclair (Folder 6)
  - Engagement calendar (Folder 7)
  - Invitations
    - 1953 (Folder 8)
    - 1954 (Folder 9)
    - 1955 (Folder 10)
    - 1956 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Letters of introduction and recommendation written by Ambassador Stuart (Folder 2)
  - Speech material - humorous (Folder 3)
  - Speeches by Ambassador Stuart
    - n.d. (Folder 4)
    - 1953 (Folder 5)
    - 1954 (Folder 6)
    - 1955 (Folder 7)
    - 1956 (Folder 8)
  - Subject file (Box 9)
    - Canada. House of Commons (Folder 1)
    - Canadian Club Project (Folder 2)
    - Colombo Plan (Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 4)
    - U.S.-Canadian relations - Speeches by Douglas Copland, A. D. P. Heeney, L. B. Pearson, Donald R. Richberg, and others (Folder 5-6)
- CANADIAN-AMERICAN COMMITTEE, 1956-1969 (Box 10-18)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, resolutions, studies, speeches, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Contribution records
    - Member companies
      - 1961-1964 (Folder 2)
      - 1965-1966 (Folder 3)
      - 1967 (Folder 4)
      - 1968 (Folder 5)
    - Non-members
      - 1961-1962 (Folder 6)
      - 1963-1964 (Folder 7)
      - 1965-1966 (Folder 8)
    - Potential contributors (Folder 9)
    - Refusal letters (Folder 10)
    - U.S. contributors - American Finance Committee (Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Miller, John (Secretariat) (Folder 1-2)
    - Stuart, Robert D.
      - General (Folder 3)
      - With Alex McBain (United Funds Canada, Ltd.) (Folder 4)
      - With R. M. Fowler (chairman, Private Planning Association of Canada and co-chairman, Canadian-American Committee) (Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 6)
  - Executive committee membership correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Founding documents (Folder 2)
  - Membership lists and correspondence, 1960-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Minutes of meetings and related correspondence, 1957-1967 (Folder 4-5)
  - Publications lists (Folder 6)
  - Reprints of memoranda and studies spondored by the Canadian-American Committee and the the Private Planning Association of Canada (Box 13)
  - Research program files (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, including one by Robert D. Stuart, October 15, 1956 (Folder 2)
  - Subject file
    - Agricultural surplus disposal (Folder 3)
    - Canadian economic goals to, 1970 (Folder 4)
    - Canadian Royal Commission on Publications (Folder 5)
    - Capital flows (Folder 6)
    - Columbia River Basin (Folder 7)
    - Cuba, Canada's trade with (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Defense production/development sharing (Folder 2)
    - Europe
      - Attitudes (Folder 3)
      - Common Market (Folder 4)
    - Fresh water (Folder 5)
    - Grain (Folder 6)
    - Lumber (Folder 7)
    - Natural gas (Folder 8)
    - North American common market for capital (Folder 9)
    - North American energy resources (Folder 10)
    - Oil (Folder 11)
    - Organization of American States (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Power (electric and other) (Folder 2)
    - Saint Lawrence Seaway (Folder 3)
    - Soviet Union - growth of economic power (Folder 4)
    - Taxation in Canada (Folder 5)
    - Trade
      - Barriers (Folder 6)
      - Expansion Act, 1962 (Folder 7)
      - Free Trade Agreement (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Non-merchandise transactions (Folder 2)
    - University of Chicago plan (Folder 3)
    - U.S.-Canadian relations
      - General (Folder 4-5)
      - Commercial (Folder 6)
      - Cultural (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Institutional (Folder 2)
      - Labor (Folder 3)
    - U.S. barter program (Folder 4)
    - U.S. business in Canada (Folder 5)
    - U.S. import quotas (Folder 6)
    - U.S. investments in Canada (Folder 7)
    - U.S. subsidiaries in Canada (Folder 8)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL (Box 19)
  Citations, declarations, prayers, etchings, sketches, as well as oversize and mounted photographs.
  - Citation to R. D. Stuart presented by the Foundation for American Agriculture, May 19, 1964 (Box 19)
  - Declaration of Independence, July 4, 1776
  - Etching depicting the steps of St. Paul's Cathedral, London
  - "The President's Prayer" offered by Dwight D. Eisenhower before beginning his Inaugural Address, January 20, 1953
  - Sketch of Dwight D. Eisenhower
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 19)
  - 1 print depicting a B-24 Liberator Bomber of USAF flying above palms of Makin Island; 1 print depicting Herbert Hoover (autographed to R. Douglas Stuart); 1 print depicting the Reunion Dinner of the Industrial Advisory Board, Washington D.C., March 7, 1934; and 1 print depicting a musk ox (Box 19)
  - 2 prints depicting General Douglas MacArthur undated (Envelope A)